<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The fall of a great visible idol by the coming of the invisible povver, and substance In this day and time of the lambs war which is come. Wherein Christ the true light is exalted at the right hand of God, who dwells and walkes in his people which are his temple. Which doth bring down the boasting baptists that hath highly exalted themselves upon the high and dark  mountains of their own imaginations, as may be known by their own principles which are herein answered with something to the simple hearted that are among them, concerning water baptism and breaking of outward bread, which these baptists hath so much idolized in the night. From a true friend unto all that loves truth in the inward parts, in true love and pitty unto the lost sheep, that they may be of the house of Israel. Joseph Fuce.</title>
            <author>Fuce, Joseph.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 93 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A40523</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F2257A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R221567</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99832865</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99832865</idno>
            <idno type="VID">37340</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A40523)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 37340)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2187:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The fall of a great visible idol by the coming of the invisible povver, and substance In this day and time of the lambs war which is come. Wherein Christ the true light is exalted at the right hand of God, who dwells and walkes in his people which are his temple. Which doth bring down the boasting baptists that hath highly exalted themselves upon the high and dark  mountains of their own imaginations, as may be known by their own principles which are herein answered with something to the simple hearted that are among them, concerning water baptism and breaking of outward bread, which these baptists hath so much idolized in the night. From a true friend unto all that loves truth in the inward parts, in true love and pitty unto the lost sheep, that they may be of the house of Israel. Joseph Fuce.</title>
                  <author>Fuce, Joseph.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 35, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Thomas Simmons, at the Bull and Mouth near Aldersgate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656 [i.e. 1659]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Date of publication misnumbered 1656; actual date of publication is 1659, cf. Smith and internal text.</note>
                  <note>Copies have date of publication obscured by MS. to read 1659.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Friends' House Library, London (Early English books) and the British Library (Misc. Brit. tracts).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Baptists --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Quakers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:37340:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE FALL OF A Great Viſible Idol By the coming of the INVISIBLE POWER, And SUBSTANCE.</p>
            <p>In this day and time of <hi>the Lambs War</hi> which is come.</p>
            <p>Wherein <hi>Chriſt the true Light</hi> is exalted at the right hand of God, who dwells and walkes in his people which are his Temple.</p>
            <p>Which doth bring down the boaſting Baptiſts that hath highly exalted themſelves upon the high and dark mountains of their own imaginations, as may be known by their own principles which are herein anſwered with ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to the ſimple hearted that are among them, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing water baptiſm and breaking of outward bread, which theſe Baptiſts hath ſo much Idolized in the night.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord, curſed be the man that truſteth in man, and maketh fleſh his Arm, and whoſe heart departeth from the Lord, for he ſhall be like the heath in the deſert, and ſhall not ſee when good co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eth,</hi> 
               <bibl>Jer 17. 5. 6.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <hi>And bleſſed is the man that truſteth in the Lord, and whoſe hope the Lord is,</hi> 
               <bibl>Jer. 17. 7,</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <hi>for it is the ſpirit that quickneth, the fleſh preſiteth nothing, the words that I ſpeak unto you they are ſpirit, and they are life,</hi> 
               <bibl>John 6. 63.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>From a true friend unto all that loves truth in the inward parts, in true love and pitty unto the loſt ſheep, that they may be of the houſe of Iſrael. <hi>Joſeph Fuce.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Simmons,</hi> at the Bull and Mouth near Alderſgate, 165<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:37340:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:37340:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>This is to the <hi>Reader</hi> that he may the better underſtand.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>NOw firſt of all (before thou comest to the matter hereafter writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten) thou art to be turned unto a meaſure of the true light in thy own conſcience, and with it to ſearch thine own heart, and to ſee whether there be not envie or prejudice lodging in thee against the way of truth, which hath been ſo abominably abuſed and evil ſpoken of, as if it were the moſt damnable Hereſie that ever was declared, in ſo much that people hath often been stirred up by their Teachers into a great rage against the truth, before they know it, or hath heard us declare it, or ſeen our writings (ſo as to understand the matter) and therefore if there be any of the envious ones leaven in thee, let that be laid aſide, and wait thou in the light, not turning to the one hand, nor yet to the other, not joyning with me nor againſt me, before thou doeſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand rightly the things there ſpoken of in love to thy poor ſoul, but wait in the pure fear of the Lord to feel the Power of God to ariſe within, and rent the vail which hath been over thy heart, that ſo the meaſure of the true light may come up in thee to bare rule, ſo as to give thee the true knowledge and the right underſtanding, for happy is the man that findeth wiſdom, and the man that getteth underſtanding, for it is better then the gain of gold, and except the light make theſe things manifest thou canst not understand this which I have ſpoken of, in the wiſdom of God which I have received, &amp; this knowledge cometh a far off (the wiſdom of the fleſh) there<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ore I will aſcribe wiſdom and righteouſneſs unto my Maker, for he that is perfect in knowledge is with God the fountain of wiſdom &amp; true knowledge, and verily I ſhall leave the truth of my words to anſwer the witneſs in thy own conſcience, and be thou ſo honeſt to thy own ſoul (before thou judgest) to try theſe things aright with that which will not lie in thee, that is the true ballance and juſt weight that weigheth things a right, that ſo thou mayest come to be perſwaded (in thy own minde) who are in the truth it ſelf, that gives true peace unto the ſoul, and who are in the profeſſion of the truth with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the poſſeſſion, in the hypocriſie, but have no true peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And truely I have ſeen the hypocriſie, and great deceit of thoſe Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts many times, at ſeveral places where they have oppoſed the very life</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:37340:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>of truth withal the ſtrength and ſubtilty they have received from the wicked one to deceive the hearts of the ſimple even to the grieving of my ſoul, to think that ever theſe Baptiſts ſhould ſo impudently gainſay the truth and life of what they proſeſs in words, and often I have been moved of the Lord in the power of the ſpirit, to reprove them for their lies and falſe accuſations, which they have brought againſt us that witneſs forth the truth, against their deceit, and when I have ſo done, I have had peace in the light, and did not deſire nor think to lay their wickedneſs open unto the world in Print, but rather deſired they ſhould have owned reproof and repented, and have turned unto the Lord in time (as ſome hath done that did walk with them) but they have deſpiſed reproof, and hated instruction, and ſet themſelves againſt the light and ſpirit of the Lord, until his anger is kindled against them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And now ſeeing how they have ſet themſelves against the truth, and will not ceaſe to pervert the right way in going on in their d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ceit, bending their tongues like a bow for lyes, thereby to deceive the hearts of the ſimple; Therefore the Lord hath put it into my heart to begin to lay open their wickedneſs (in Print) for the truths ſake, and in true love and pitty to the poor ſimple-hearted people, that they may not run ſo raſhly into their ſnares, to go with them they know not whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, until their ſteps take hold on Hell; for they have openly denied the true light, as is hereafter mentioned, and they that walk in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs know not whether they go; and therefore thou that lovest thy own Souls peace, be warned in time to weigh things rightly with that which is a Juſt weight and true Meaſure in thy own Conſcience, ſo mayeſt thou come to be perſwaded in thy own mind who are in the right way, and then let the light be thy guide in it to walk, that ſo thou mayeſt come in due time to have peace with God in the Covenant of light and life for evermore.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:37340:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>At a Meeting at</hi> Nethurſt, <hi>upon the</hi> 24th <hi>of the</hi> 6th <hi>Month, 1659. appointed by</hi> Matthew Caffin <hi>Baptiſt, but there were ſeveral of the chief Baptists in all theſe South parts, namely,</hi> William Jeffery, Matthew Caf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin, John Parſons, William Steel, <hi>and ſeveral others of</hi> Kent <hi>and</hi> Suſſex.</head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>It was pretended by the Baptists, there to ſhew the cauſe wherefore they could not joyn with the</hi> Quakers, <hi>as they with other ſcoffers in theſe laſt times call us the People of the Lord; but in ſtead of proving any Juſt cauſe why they do not own and joyn with us, they gave ſufficient cauſe for us (and all that fear the Lord) to deny them, and to have no fellowſhip with them, except they repent.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>And the cauſe they gave us at this Meeting (and at other places) was thoſe errours, damnable hereſies and lyes, which are hereafter mentioned and anſwered, as moved by the Spirit of love to all the ſimple-hearted people, that doth deſire to walk in the way of truth unto</hi> Zion <hi>the City of the living God, where Peace is to be enjoyed for evermore.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt the Baptiſt affirmed, <hi>That the Eternal Spirit that was in Chriſt was not the Saviour of the world.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Here they deny the true God to be the Saviour of the world, who was in Chriſt the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour of Eternal Salvation, the ground and foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of all truth, who is a Spirit and is Eternal, and God the Father, and Chriſt the Son (whoſe Name is called the Word of God) and the Eternal Spirit or Holy Ghoſt are one, and the Father was in the Son, and the Son was in the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:37340:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> Father, <hi>John</hi> 14. 11. and he that hath ſeen the Son hath <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oh 10. 30</note> ſeen the Father, and God who is the onely Inviſible and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Spirit, ſaved all the holy men of God in the dayes of old ſince the beginning, and when the old world was drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned God ſaved <hi>Noah, 2 Pet.</hi> 2. 5. and the Eternal God ſaid by the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> Look unto me and be ye ſaved all the ends of the earth, for I am God and there is none elſe, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45. 22. there is no God effectual beſides the Eternal Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that is a Juſt God and a Saviour, <hi>verſ.</hi> 21. and this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour ſaid, <hi>I, even I am the Lord, and beſides me there is no Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour,</hi> Iſa. 43. 11. And the Apoſtle ſaid, <hi>The Lord is the Spirit,</hi> 2 Cor. 3. 17. and this Eternal God (who is a Spirit) was he that ſaved all the holy men of God, and they both Prophets and Apoſtles called God their Saviour, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 10. <hi>Titus</hi> 7. 3. and this Everlaſting God and Eternal Spirit, (that was the <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Pet. 1. 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ude 25.</note> onely Saviour of all the holy men of God) the Apoſtle ſaid, to wit, <hi>That God was in Chriſt reconciling the world unto himſelf,</hi> 2 Cor. 5. 19. and Chriſt was in God, and ſometime the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle called Chriſt Lord and Saviour, and they alſo called God their Saviour, for they were one in the beginning be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the world was; but the Baptiſts doth not ſee how Chriſt <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ut the bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y without <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he Spirit is dead, <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>am.</hi> 2. 26.</note> and God are one, as one of them ſaid, and therefore denies the Eternal Spirit, that was and is in Chriſts body to be the Saviour; and ſo blaſpemouſly hath denied both the Father and the Son, and there is no Saviour beſides the Eternal Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, which was God manifeſt in the fleſh; and if any ſhould read this, and not perceive the things of God, and ſo not believe the Words of truth; read the 13th of <hi>Hoſea,</hi> and 14th <hi>verſe,</hi> were God ſaith, <hi>Yet I am the Lord thy God from the land of</hi> Egypt, <hi>and thou ſhalt know no God but me, for there is no Saviour beſide me;</hi> and all thoſe that readeth this with a right underſtanding may ſee and perceive the Baptiſts to be ignorant of the Power of God; and alſo of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, which doth ſo largely ſpeak of that God (that was in Chriſt) to be the onely Saviour; but time might fail us to bring all thoſe Scriptures which doth ſpeak of God to be the Saviour.</p>
               <p>Baptiſts Affirmed, <hi>That Chriſt was not come to them yet the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond time, nor yet to any man upon the face of the earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:37340:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Here the Baptiſts hath manifeſted themſelves open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be Reprobates according to the Scripture, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is no marvel why they oppoſe the light in others ſo much, ſeeing they deny Chriſt the light to be come to them the ſecond time, and there were ſuch in the Apoſtles dayes that ſought a proof of Chriſt ſpeaking in the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> who ſaid unto them, <hi>Examine your ſelves whether ye be in the Faith, prove your own ſelves, know you not your own ſelves how that Jeſus Chriſt is in you except ye be Reprobates?</hi> 2 Cor. 13. 5. and now you may ſee the Baptiſts, yea the very chief among them are Reprobates, out of the Faith the Saints were in, who preached Chriſt in them the Hope of Glory, and ſaid, He is come that is true, and they were in him that is true, even in his Son Jeſus Chriſt; and ſo they that did receive him at his coming to dwell in them, he gave them an underſtanding how to preach him up in others, and alſo in Heaven at the right hand of God; but they that do not know him come to them, they do not know him in any other Creature in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven or in earth, and where the true Chriſt the Son of God who is a quickning Spirit doth not Rule, there the Antichriſt ruleth, the ſon of perdition ruleth, the old man of ſin reign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in them and over them, and he maketh them ſubject to ſin; and now Antichriſt is come up very high in theſe Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts, and he doth appear very bold in them, inſomuch that they deny the true Chriſt to be come the ſecond time to them or to any other Creature, but the Scripture is ſo far a witneſs againſt them that all the moderate people may ſee that they are ignorant of the things of God, and alſo of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and ſo altogether unfit to preach unto others; for how can any truly preach Chriſt to come to others, that doth not know him come unto themſelves, <hi>Paul</hi> was a perſecutor before he knew Chriſt revealed in him, but after it pleaſed God to reveal his Son in him, then he was fit to preach the manner of his coming in others, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1. 16. and Chriſt ſaid unto his Diſciples, he dwelleth with you and ſhall be in you, I will not leave you comfortleſs, I will come to you, <hi>John</hi> 14. 18. and <hi>John</hi> in his Epiſtle ſaid, We know that the Son of God is come, and hath given us an underſtanding that we may know him that is true, and we are in him that is true,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:37340:5"/> even in his Son Jeſus Chriſt, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5. 20. here <hi>John</hi> ſaid he is come, but the Baptiſts ſaith he is not come, and ſo are out of the Faith and Doctrine that the Apoſtles were in; and <hi>John</hi> ſpake of ſuch falſe prophets that were entred into the world as theſe Baptiſts are, who confeſs not that Jeſus Chriſt is come in the fleſh, this is a deceiver and an Antichriſt, 2 <hi>John</hi> 7. (Mark) he doth not ſay there, he that denies that he was come, or ſhall come, but he ſaith, who confeſs not that he is come in the fleſh (Mark that) for both Papiſts and other Prieſts, and the Baptiſts and we do all believe that he did come in the fleſh, and was crucified without the Gates of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> and alſo that he ſhall come at the laſt day to Judge the quick and the dead, according to the Scriptures; but this is the great controverſie which we have with all thoſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout this matter, that is, whether Jeſus Chriſt be manifeſted or come in the fleſh now according to the Scripture; but all that reſiſt the light that lighteth every man that cometh into the world, they reſiſt the true Chriſt which the Apoſtles and we ſay is come in the fleſh, and they receive the Spirit of Antichriſt, and become one with that, and ſo reſiſt the true light, the true comforter, the man of ſorrows, that puts an end to ſin; and <hi>John</hi> in the Spirit or the Spirit in <hi>John,</hi> ſaid in the Revelation, Behold I ſtand at the door and knock, if any man hear my voice and open the door, I will come in to him, and will ſup with him and he with me, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3. 20. he that hath an ear let him hear what the Spirit ſaith.</p>
               <p>The Baptiſt denied, <hi>That Chriſt was that crucified oftener then once.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Here you may ſee the Baptiſts chief principles are to deny the true Chriſt the Son of God, who proceeded from the Father to ſeek and to ſave that which was loſt; but the Baptiſts renders evil againſt him that came for good unto all men, even to the loſt, to ſeek and to ſave that which was loſt, and he giveth to every man that which is good, this is the true light which lighteth every man that cometh into the world, and this is he the Baptiſts deny, and whom the Jews were ſo much againſt, and did often deny him,, ſaying, Crucifie him, crucifie him, and releaſe unto us <hi>Barrabas,</hi> and he was crucified without the Gates at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> at the place which
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:37340:5"/> is called <hi>Calvary, Luk.</hi> 23. 33. there was one time ſpoke of where Chriſt was crucified without the Gates, and after that <hi>John</hi> ſaid he was crucified in the ſtreets of the great City, which ſpiritually is called <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Egypt, Rev.</hi> 11. 8. that was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother time and place ſpoken of; and the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> who had been a perſecutor, and was converted after Chriſts ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring (without the Gate at <hi>Jeruſalem)</hi> and after the Church was gathered and grown up (ſo as to taſte of the good Word of God, and the power of the World to come) then he writes to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> concerning ſome that crucified to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the Son of God afreſh, and put him to an open ſhame, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. 6. the Son of God was the true Chriſt, which was crucified by the Jews without the Gates at <hi>Calvary,</hi> and in ſpiritual <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Egypt,</hi> and alſo by ſuch as departed from the Faith; for they crucified to themſelves the Son of God afreſh (take notice of that) That you may ſee plainly how the Baptiſts deny the true Chriſt, the Son of God, the Lamb ſlain from the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oundation of the world.</p>
               <p>The Baptiſts affirmed, <hi>That the Comforter ſpoken of in that</hi> 14th <hi>of</hi> John <hi>to come again to the Diſciples, was not Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Chriſt in that 14th of <hi>John</hi> ſaid, the Father ſhould give them another <hi>Comforter;</hi> but he did not ſay it was not Chriſt that ſhould come to them which was then with them, but on the contrary ſaid, he dwelleth with you and ſhall be in you, <hi>verſ.</hi> the 17th. and ſo he was to be known after ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther manner, not after the fleſh without them, for he was ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted unto them in that form of fleſh, and ſo became of no reputation, and paſſed thorow outward things, and ſuffered the contradictions of ſinners in the time of doing his Fathers Will, for which he was ſent in that form; then when all was fulfilled, both outward Baptiſm with water, and outward Circumciſion with hands, then he ſaid, all is finiſhed, and gave up the Ghoſt, and went to the Father from whence he proceeded, and then was there no neceſſity of thoſe out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward things, nor Command to do them from God as before, becauſe they were fulfilled, yet for a time they were a little uſed by them that came unto all in thoſe things, that they might win ſome out of all thoſe things (which was to decreaſe) up to Chriſt that was to increaſe and prevail mightily in thoſe
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:37340:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> with whom he dwelt until he went to the Father, and after he was riſen he appeared unto his Diſciples in another form, and after that he appeared in them, they did not tell people of his being among any people without them as he was known; but ſaid, know you not your own ſelves how that Jeſus Chriſt is in you, except you be Reprobates; but theſe Baptiſts they deny his ſo coming again, and ſaith it was not Chriſt, although Chriſt ſaid ſo plainly in <hi>John</hi> 14. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. &amp; if I go &amp; prepare a place for you, I will come again and receive you unto my ſelf; and in <hi>verſ.</hi> the 18th Chriſt ſaid unto them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, I will not leave you comfortleſs, I will come to you, but the Baptiſts ſaid it was not he, and ſo would make Chriſt the lyar, in as much as they can, with their lying divina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of their own brain, ſaying, the Comforter there ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of was not Chriſt, although he himſelf ſaid, I will come to you, and <hi>John</hi> ſaid he was come unto them, and they were in him, even in his Son Jeſus Chriſt, this is the true God and Eternal life; little Children keep your ſelves from Idols, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5. 20, 21.</p>
               <p>The Baptiſts affirmed, <hi>That it was Blaſphemy to ſay that thoſe things ſpoken of to Chriſts Diſciples in</hi> Matth. 24. <hi>was fulfilled in that age.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Chriſt ſaid then to his Diſciples, many ſhould come in his Name, ſaying, I am Chriſt, and ſhall deceive many, and ſaid, Lo here, or lo there is Chriſt, believe them not, go not forth, for the true Chriſt was to be known with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in them, and he ſaid unto them, they ſhould hear of wars and rumors of wars, and earth-quakes was to be, and the love of many ſhall wax cold, becauſe iniquity ſhall abound; and the Diſciples was to be afflicted and perſecuted, and kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led at the laſt of their age, and the Sun was to be darkned, and the Moon was not to give her light for a time, and all theſe things is ſpoken in the 24th of <hi>Matthew,</hi> and the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures there and in other places doth plainly prove that theſe things were to come to paſs in the Apoſtles age; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſt bids them watch, and be alwayes ready, becauſe the time was nigh, but the day and hour no man was to know until it came; and Chriſt ſaid to his Diſciples, <hi>Matth. 24. 34. Verily I ſay unto you, this Generation ſhall not paſs till all theſe things</hi>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:37340:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
                  <hi>be fulfilled;</hi> and in the 14th <hi>verſe</hi> Chriſt ſaid, <hi>And this Goſpel of the Kingdom ſhall be preached in all the world for a witneſs to all Nations, and then ſhall the end come;</hi> but the Baptiſts counts that blaſphemy for us to affirm that the end of all thoſe things was come, and ſo fulfilled in the Diſciples age before that Generation paſſed away, as Chriſt ſaid; Further I ſhall prove out of the Scriptures that theſe things did come to paſs.</p>
               <p>Firſt concerning falſe Prophets and Antichriſts, they were to come unto the true Prophets and Apoſtles, to deceive them (if it were poſſible) and they did ſo come as Chriſt ſaid they ſhould; and the Diſciples, Apoſtles and Prophets that did watch (as Chriſt ſaid they ſhould) they did ſee the falſe prophets and deceivers come privily in the very form of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, but denying the power thereof, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. and <hi>John</hi> ſaid in his firſt Epiſtle 2. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Little Children, it is the laſt time, and as ye have heard that Antichriſt ſhall come, even now are there many Antichriſts, whereby we know it is the laſt time;</hi> and <hi>John</hi> ſaid, <hi>Many falſe prophets are gone out into the world,</hi> 1 John 4. 1. but firſt they came unto the Church, but they reſiſted them, and overcame them, and then they went into the world, and the world heard them, <hi>verſ.</hi> 4. 5. and ſo hath the world been deceived ever ſince the Apoſtles dayes, in the night which Chriſt ſpake of to come wherein no man could work; but if I ſhould undertake to declare as much as might be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of both of the true Apoſtles and Prophets, and falſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles and prophets, ſurely time would fail me, but this is a ſufficient proof for this particular; alſo the Diſciples were to ſee <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> compaſſed about with Armies, and then was there wars, and the Sun and Moon was to be darkned, and there was to be earth-quakes, and there was darkneſs, for it was ſaid from the ſixth hour there was darkneſs over all the Land unto the ninth hour, <hi>Mat.</hi> 27. 45. and when Jeſus cryed with a loud voice and yielded up the Ghoſt, behold, the vail of the Temple was rent in twain, from the top to the bottom, and the earth did quake, and the rocks rent, and the graves were opened, and many bodies of Saints aroſe, <hi>Mat.</hi> 27. 50, 51, 52. And Chriſt ſaid the Goſpel ſhould be preached in all the world, for a witneſs unto all Nations, (Mark) and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:37340:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> then ſhall the end come. And when <hi>Paul</hi> queſtioned whether the Goſpel had been ſo preached, he ſaid, have they not heard? yea verily, their ſound went into all the earth, and their Words unto the ends of the world, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 18. and then came the end of all thoſe things according to Chriſt his Words; but the Baptiſts call that Blaſphemy.</p>
               <p>The Baptiſts affirmed, <hi>That neither</hi> Abraham, <hi>nor</hi> Iſaac, Peter <hi>nor</hi> Paul <hi>was redeemed from the curſe, nor out of the fall, nor are not yet; neither is</hi> Abraham, Iſaac <hi>nor</hi> Jacob <hi>in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The fall of man was into tranſgreſſion of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Law and Command of the righteous God of Heaven and earth, and ſo man fell from God out of that ſtate which he was created in, into ſin and iniquity, which ſeparated be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween God and man, yet God had an eye of pitty unto man in that fallen ſinful ſeparated condition, and God made a Covenant with man whereby man might come again unto himſelf out of the fall, and the Covenant was, that the ſeed of the woman ſhould bruiſe the ſerpents head which temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and led away into ſin, that ſo man might come again un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God out of ſin, and ſo the Seed or Word of God (which was with God before the World was made) became as a <note place="margin">Gen. 14. 19. Gen. 15. 1. Gen. 22. Gen. 17.</note> hammer unto the head of the ſerpent to bruiſe it; and God talked with <hi>Abraham</hi> when he appeared unto him, as a man talketh with his familiar Friend, and God bleſſed him, and made a Covenant with him, and changed his name from <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bram</hi> to <hi>Abraham,</hi> for a Father of many Nations have I made thee ſaid the Almighty, whoſe everlaſting Covenant was with <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Seed for ever, and the Covenant was to be in their fleſh, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. 3. and <hi>Abraham</hi> the Father of the faithful was perfect and did ſee Chriſts day, and he rejoyced to ſee Chriſts glorious day, who ſaid, before <hi>Abraham</hi> was I am, <hi>John</hi> 8. 56. 58. And <hi>Noah</hi> was perfect and God ſaved him; and <hi>Enock</hi> was tranſlated by Faith, that he ſhould not ſee death, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. and they were redeemed out of the fall, and from under the curſe up to God, who bleſſed <hi>Abraham</hi> the Father of the faithful, and they that were of Faith pleaſed God, &amp; were &amp; are bleſſed; but they that were of the wicked one, and did alwayes reſiſt the holy Ghoſt, they were and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:37340:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> are under the curſe in the fall, and the wrath of the juſt God comes upon them, but <hi>Enoch</hi> and <hi>Noah</hi> walked with God, <hi>Gen. 5. 22. Gen.</hi> 6. 9. and <hi>David</hi> ſaid, Into thine hand I commit my Spirit, thou haſt redeemed me O Lord God of truth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Now the Baptiſts in the envy and bitterneſs of their ſpirit hath manifeſted their ignorance of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, and alſo of Redemption out of the fall, in ſaying thoſe notable holy men of God were not redeemed out of the fall. But now thus ſaith the Lord that created thee O <hi>Jacob</hi> and he that formed thee O <hi>Iſrael,</hi> fear not, for I have redeemed thee, I have called thee by my name, thou art mine, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <note place="margin">Iſai. 63. 9.</note> and the Apoſtle <hi>paul</hi> when he ſpake even to this very thing concerning himſelf, and they that were redeemed from un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the curſe (mark that) he ſaith, Chriſt hath redeemed us from the curſe of the Law, &amp;c <hi>Gal.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 13. and <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid they were not redeemed with corruptable things, as ſilver and gold, from your vain converſation received by tradition from your fathers, but with the precious blood of Chriſt, as of a Lamb without blemiſh &amp; without ſpot, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 18. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>9. and ſo it doth appear they were redeemed unto God the Judge of all by the blood of the Covenant, or Lamb ſlain from the foundation of the world, and the Saints and Elders which were in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven were redeemed unto God, out of every kindred, and and tongue, and People and Nation, and they ſang a new ſong, ſaying, Thou art worthy to take the book and to open the Seals thereof, for thou waſt ſlain and haſt-redeemed us to God by thy blood out of every kindred, and tongue, and People, and Nation, <hi>Revel.</hi> 5. 9. and the Saints converſation was in heaven, and are in the Kingdom of Heaven, although the baptiſts ſay, neither <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> nor <hi>Jacob</hi> was in the Kingdom, neither are they yet in the Kingdom ſaith the Baptiſts, who ſhuts up the Kingdom of Heaven againſt men, for they neither go in themſelves, neither ſuffer they them that are entering in to goin, and ſo are found in the Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees and Hypocrites practices, ſee <hi>Mat.</hi> 23, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. there was enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into the Kingdom then, and there was thoſe that did hinder men from going into the Kingdom then, and as it was then ſo it is now, as it doth appear by theſe Baptiſts that ſay neither <hi>Abraham, Iſaac</hi> nor <hi>Jacob</hi> was in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:37340:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> and ſo are found out of Chriſts Doctrine, and altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther contrary to his words, as they are in the Scriptures of truth; which are profitable for correction (of ſuch un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable talkers as theſe envious ignorant Baptiſts are) and for inſtruction of the ſimple; now when Chriſt ſpoke of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> he ſaid they were in the Kingdom, but the Baptiſts ſay they are not in the Kingdom. Now when you have read the Baptiſts words, and Chriſts words, then let the witneſs be Judge who is the lyar. And I ſay unto you that many ſhall come from the Eaſt and Weſt, and ſhall ſit down with <hi>Abraham,</hi> and <hi>Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> in the Kingdom of <note place="margin">Luke 16. 22.</note> Heaven, <hi>Mat.</hi> 8. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. here Chriſt ſaith with <hi>Abraham,</hi> and <hi>Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> in the Kingdom of Heaven, and in <hi>Mat.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. he ſpeaketh of entering into the Kingdom, and <hi>John</hi> ſpake of his brethren in the Kingdom <hi>Revel.</hi> 1. 9. and <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of ſome that were come unto Mount Sion, unto the City of the living God, the Heavenly Jeruſalem, &amp; to innumerable company of Angels, to the general Aſſembly and Church of the firſt born which are written in Heaven, and to God the Judge of all, and to the ſpirits of Juſt men made perfect, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 22. 23. they were redeemed out of the fall, up to God the Judge of all, and they had received the Kingdom, and were in Heaven, and all that feareth the Lord truely may ſee the Baptiſts far unfit to Preach the way into the Kingdom of God, ſeeing they are yet in the fall and Kingdom of darkneſs, and think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all others to be ſo, and there they labour (as may be ſeen by theſe principles of theirs) to keep others in darkneſs and unbelief, and ſo do not enter themſelves, neither would they have others to be tranſlated into the Kingdom of the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dear Son of God, there to find reſt and Peace for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Baptiſts affirmed that no man could come into that ſtate that</hi> Adam <hi>was created in on this ſide the grave.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> This is a denying Chriſts ſuffering to do the work which the Father ſent him about, which was to ſeek and to ſave that which was loſt, and to quicken man that was dead in treſpaſſes and ſins, and Chriſt did finiſh the work which the Father gave him to do; although the effect of the Baptiſts words is to deny it. Now ſee what the Scripture ſaith. The
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:37340:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> Son of man is come to ſave that which was loſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. 11. and the Saints were ſaved, as in 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 9. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 2. for ſince by man came death, by man came alſo the reſurrection of the dead, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 21. and this the Apoſtles witneſſed and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared unto them that had been dead in treſpaſſes and ſins on this ſide the grave, and you hath he quickned, <hi>Eph.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. (mark) for we are his workmanſhip created in Chriſt Je<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> good works, which God hath before ordained that we ſhould walk in them, verſe the 10. and ſo they were come out of the ſin and tranſgreſſion (which <hi>Adam</hi> was dead in) up to God again, who was in Chriſt reconciling the world unto himſelf, and the Law of the Spirit of life did make them free from the Law of ſin and death on this ſide the grave, and then there was no condemnation to them that were in Chriſt Jeſus which walked not after the fleſh but after the Spirit, and that was on this ſide the grave, for they could do nothing againſt the truth but for the truth in Chriſt Jeſus, who is the expreſſe Image of his Fathers Perſon, and in him and by him was man created in Chriſt Jeſus; and the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid on this ſide the grave, O death where is thy ſting, O grave where is thy victory? the ſting of death is ſin, and the ſtrength of ſin is the Law, but thanks be to God which giveth us the victory <note place="margin">Eccl. 11. 3.</note> through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. and if victory be not received on this ſide the grave (which theſe Baptiſts ſpeak of) it will not be at all known unto them that are cut off in their ſins; for where the tree falleth there it lyeth, whether it be to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the North or towards the ſouth, for the time is at hand, he that is unjuſt, let him be unjuſt ſtill, and he which is filthy let him be filthy ſtill, &amp; he that is righteous let him be righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſtill, and he that is holy let him be holy ſtill, <hi>Revel.</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 11. he that can receive it let him.</p>
               <p>Matthew Caſfin <hi>one of the Baptiſts affirmed, that if he were in that firſt ſtate that</hi> Adam <hi>was created in he ſhould not be mortal, nor thirſty, ſick nor weary.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Thou that ſayeſt neither <hi>Abraham,</hi> nor <hi>Iſaac,</hi> nor <hi>Peter</hi> nor <hi>Paul</hi> was redeemed from the curſe, nor from the fall, and that no man could come into that ſtate that <hi>Adam</hi> was created in on this ſide the grave, thou haſt manifeſted <note place="margin">Zach. 5. 1. 2.</note> thy ſelf to be yet in the fall, in ſin and darknes, and tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:37340:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> not yet come to <hi>Adams</hi> firſt eſtate; which was a living ſoul, but under the curſe which is gone forth, as a fiery flying rowl; and in that fallen eſtate thou haſt exalted thy ſelf over a people to be their Teacher, who counts themſelves members of the Church of Chriſt; for how canſt thou tell what thou ſhouldſt have done, that art not come to <hi>Adams</hi> firſt eſtate (mark) yet art intruding into thoſe things wch thou knoweſt not, as it appeareth by thy ſaying thou ſhouldſt not be mortal, thirſty, ſick nor weary, and it is no marvel to me to ſee ſuch contention and confuſion among thoſe Baptiſts that doth own ſuch meſſengers that comes in their own name, which are not redeemed out of the fall into <hi>Adams</hi> firſt eſtate, but art in the will worſhip, beguiling unſtable ſouls through thy voluntary humility, intruding into thoſe things which thou haſt not ſeen, vainly puft up by thy fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mind, and all may read there were ſuch, <hi>Col.</hi> 2 18. and they that are not yet hardened amongſt thoſe ſcattered peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that were once made tender (by ſomething of God in their conſciences which they knew not) oh I ſay let them with ſpeed return their minds again to the witneſs in them, and that will let them ſee how the Lords hand is and hath been much againſt the Baptiſts ſince they reſiſted the light; therefore he hath ſcattered them ſo much in their imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that they are divided into opinions like the Prieſts, and therefore it is high time for all people that fear the Lord to come out from among them, and wait in the light of Chriſt, which would then appear to lead them out of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, by the footſteps of the flock, toward the reſt at Noon, <hi>Cant.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>The Baptiſts at that meeting affirmed, <hi>that the light which we Preach (whom they call</hi> Quakers) <hi>they do deny, and trample under foot, but</hi> John Lukes <hi>at a meeting ſoon after appealed to the light in every ones conſeience which</hi> Joſeph Fuce ſpoke of.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Here the Baptiſts hath declared the very cauſe why they are in ſo much confuſion, errours and Popiſh Doctrine and lies, and ſo full of envy and bitterneſs of ſpirit againſt us the people of the Lord, which bears witneſs unto the true light which is Chriſt, ſeeing that they deny the light which we Preach, and trample it under foot (as one of their chief
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:37340:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> Teachers ſaid) but another ſaid, he appealed to the light in every ones conſcience, which <hi>Joſeph Fuce</hi> ſpake of, which is Chriſt the true light which lighteth every man that cometh into the world, <hi>John</hi> 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. and no other do we Preach to be Chriſt but he that ſaid I am the light of the world, he that followeth me ſhall not walk in darkneſs but ſhall have the light of Life, <hi>John 8. 12. John</hi> 12. 46. which is Chriſt the true light which lighteth every man that cometh into the world, <hi>John</hi> 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. and this is the light which we have Preached up at the right hand of God, who dwells in his people according to the Scriptures, and no other Chriſt do we own but he which all the Prophets bare witneſs of, and that <hi>John</hi> ſaid was the true light, as we have proved very plainly by the Scriptures, and that thouſands of people know which are not come yet to walk in the light, but if they do not harden themſelves but fear the Name of the Lord, in due time they ſhall know the riſing of the Son of righteouſneſs with healing under his wings, and the wicked ſhall be brought down in them and for them, and now all moderate people may ſee theſe Baptiſts to be blaſted with a thick miſt, and overcome with groſſe darkneſs, who make it their work to deny the true Chriſt the Son of the onely true God, and ſo denies the Father alſo; for no other light do we Preach to be the Chriſt, the Saviour, the Son of God; but he that hath ſaid I am the light of the world, and he that believeth in him is not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, but he that believeth not is condemned already, and this is the condemnation, that light is come into the world and men love darkneſs rather then light becauſe their deed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> are evil, <hi>John</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 19. And here their Teachers are found one againſt another about the light, and now people may ſee the Apoſtles words are true who ſpake of ſuch boaſters, proud blaſphemers, having a form of godlineſs but denying the power, and now as <hi>Jannes</hi> and <hi>Jambres</hi> withſtood <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſo do theſe alſo reſiſt the truth, men of corrupt minds, repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e concerning the faith, But they ſhall proceed no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for their folly ſhall be made manifeſt to all men (that reads this with the light) as theirs alſo was. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. and take notice what <hi>Pet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r</hi> ſaith, but there were falſe Prophets alſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the people, even as there ſhall be falſe Teachers among
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:37340:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> you, who privily ſhall bring in damnable Hereſies, even de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying the Lord tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> bought them, and bring upon themſelves ſwift d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtruction, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Pet.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 1. and theſe Baptiſts that deny the E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ernal Spirit to be the Saviour of the world, and alſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e true light, and ſo they now while they are in their form crying up outward things to be Ordinances for a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, and ſo bring in damnable Hereſies. And ſo did the Phariſees (that were exceeding wicked) cry up the Temple and ſuch things, and for a pretence made long prayers, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>4. But whoſoever ſhall deny me before men, him will I alſo deny before my Father which is in Heaven ſaith Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10. 33. therefore be warned in time you that be not paſt feeling, for this I know, that it had been good for ſuch wicked blaſphemers that they had never been born, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hen ſo lightly and raſhly to deny the onely Son of God, which is the light of the world; for he that deſpiſed <hi>Moſes</hi> Law dyed without mercy under two or three witneſſes, of how much ſorer puniſhment ſuppoſe ye ſhall he be thought worthy, who hath troden under foot the Son of God, and hath counted the blood of the Covenant wherewith he was ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied as an unholy thing, and hath done deſpite unto the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of grace, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 28. 29.</p>
               <p>Another Baptiſt at <hi>Nethurſt</hi> meeting afore mentioned af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed, <hi>That Chriſt was not a Spirit, and bid one</hi> Humphery Killing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eck <hi>prove i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> if he co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ld.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> God is a ſpirit, <hi>John</hi> 4. 24. and Chriſt ſaid he and his Father was one, <hi>John</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0. 30. and he is a quickening Spirit the Scripture ſaith, but the Baptiſt ſaith he is not a ſpirit, for they make fleſh their arm, and therefore look without to know him after the fleſh, although the Apoſtles ſaid they were to know him ſo no more (mark) Thus ſaith the Lord, Curſed be the man that truſteth in man &amp; maketh fleſh his arm, and whoſe heart departeth from the Lord, for he ſhall be like the hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h in the deſert and ſhall not ſee when good cometh, <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r.</hi> 17. 5. 6. and bleſſed is the man that truſteth in the Lord and whoſe hope the Lord is, <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r</hi> 17. 7. and the quickening Spirit is both Chriſt and Lord. Now concerning Jeſus Chriſt our Lord, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w he came in the form of a man, or how he took fleſh upon him, he was of the ſeed of <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>David</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the fleſh, and declared to be the Son of God with
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:37340:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> power according to the Spirit of holineſs by the reſurrection from the dead, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. and when the fulneſs of time was come God ſent forth his Son born of a Virg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n, and made under the Law, and then he made himſelf of no reputation, but <note place="margin">Gal. 4.</note> took upon him the form of a ſervant, and ſo came under Tutors and Governours for a time, in that form of a man, or in that body which was prepared under the Law, in the time of ſigns, and types, and figures and ſhadowes of good things to come, and there was Ci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cumciſion without, and Baptiſme with<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> outward water, and Synagogues and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples made with hands, and he like unto other men came into thoſe things in that body of fleſh which he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ook upon him, and ſo fulfilled all thoſe things which did ſignifie of that which is become more excellent unto us, and ſo he paſſed through thoſe things which were but ſhadows, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd went to his Father from them as a ſhadow, for it is ſaid a cloud re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived him out of their ſight, and while he was among them in that form, he was alſo rejected and grieved to ſee their wickedneſs, in ſo much that he wept over them, and was taken by wicked hands and cruc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fied, and put to death, and ſlain and pierced by them, and was laid in a Sepulchre (a figure) and roſe again the third day according to the Scriptures, and appeared unto <hi>Mary</hi> like a gardiner, and alſo he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared unto his Diſciples in another form, <hi>Mark</hi> 16. and ſo he taſted death for every creature; for in him was life, and the life was the light of men, and he ſaid, <hi>John</hi> 10. I lay down my life that I may take it again, no man taketh it from me, but I lay it down of my ſelf, I have power to lay it down, and I have power to take it again; and ſo he took fleſh upon him and offered once for all, who perfected for ever them <note place="margin">John 6.</note> that are ſanctified, but the fleſh profiteth nothing, and he was one with the Father before the world was made, and he w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt to the Father again, and was and is one with the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and he and the Father are one, <hi>John</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0. but neither the <hi>Jews</hi> nor theſe Baptiſts doth not ſee how; for they neither know the Chriſt of God nor the Father that ſay he is not a Spirit, <hi>Joh.</hi> 8. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. but the natural man receiveth not the things of the Spirit of God for they are fooliſhneſs unto him, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can he know them, becauſe they are ſpiritually diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:37340:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. and therefore the Baptiſts being natural ſaith, Chriſt is not a Spirit, but they in whom Chriſt is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed know him to be a Spirit, as the Apoſtle ſaid, and ſo it is written, The firſt man <hi>Adam</hi> was made a living ſoul, the laſt <hi>Adam</hi> was made a quickening Spirit, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Corin.</hi> 15. 45. (mark) that you may ſee how carnal the Baptiſts are.</p>
               <p>Another Baptiſt at the aforementioned meeting affirmed, <hi>That Chriſt and God was not one.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> This is altogether contrary to theſe Scriptures which are Chriſts own words, read theſe Scriptures in the light and you need no farther proof, I and my Father are one, <hi>Joh.</hi> 10. 30. Holy Fath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r keep through thine own name thoſe whom thou haſt given me, that they may be one as we are, <hi>Joh.</hi> 17. 11. and now people may ſee with the light that is riſen in the conſcience how theſe Baptiſts hath ſeparated themſelves ſenſual, having not the Spirit, <hi>Jude</hi> 19.</p>
               <p>And when theſe Baptiſts were juſtly charged with confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, for ſpeaking three or four together to one of us, <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew Caffin</hi> ſaid to <hi>Joſeph Fuce,</hi> it was to make him ſilent; and alſo when <hi>Matthew Caffin</hi> was required to prove what he had accuſed us of, or elſe he had proved himſelf a falſe accuſer; then <hi>Matthew Caffin</hi> Baptiſt Teacher ſaid, they were fain to cavil hard with us, and many ſuch like ſwelling words and boaſting falſe accuſations and affirmations againſt the truth and us that own it; but their proud boaſting words being ſo unſavoury, I ſhall not meddle with them all, they are too many, but thoſe that are ſo much againſt the truth, I am conſtrained to anſwer for the truths ſake, and in the Power of the Spirit did I juſtifie the truth againſt its gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayers to their faces, and then they fled into confuſion and cavilling, making uſe of that to make us ſilent, (as <hi>Matthew Caffin</hi> ſaid) and all that doth underſtand the Scriptures of truth knoweth ſuch there were, and ſuch there are, as <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid, There ſhall be falſe Teachers among you, who privily ſhall bring in damnable hereſies, even denying the Lord that bought them, and bring upon themſelves ſwift deſtruction, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 1. Now if their hearts ſhould be vexed, becauſe their <note place="margin">Ezek. 3. 9.</note> folly is ſo manifeſted openly, they may blame themſelves, for theſe damnable hereſies were taken from their own
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:37340:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> mouths at the meeting aforementioned, and moſt of them were affirmed by <hi>Matthew Caffin</hi> one of their chief Teachers, who ſaid, they were fain to cavil hard, and uſe confuſion to make us ſilent; who did then as at other times earneſtly contend for the Faith which was once delivered unto the <note place="margin">Jude 3.</note> Saints; but now mark what <hi>James</hi> ſaid, <hi>But if ye have bitte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, envying and ſtrife in your hearts, glory not and ly' not again<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> truth, this wiſdom deſcendeth not from above, but is earthly, ſenſual, deviliſhſ, or where envying and ſtrife is, there is confuſion and every evil work,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ames 3. 14, 15, 16. And thoſe Baptiſts were found boaſting themſelves enviou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly, and cavilling hard, and in confuſion, as <hi>Matthew Caffin</hi> ſaid, and gloried into his own ſhame, and the reſt of the Baptiſts that reſiſt the truth, let it be eſpecially to them that were with him and did not reprove him; ſuch as is here mentioned and anſwered, have they often brought forth ſince they oppoſed the light and gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayed the truth, and ſo by their fruits are they known unto thoſe that do not wilfully reſiſt the light.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>More of the Baptiſts Principles declared and affirmed by</hi> Matthew Caffin <hi>(Baptiſt Teacher)</hi> at another time and place, as is hereafter mentioned, at <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chester</hi> upon the 30th day of the 3d month, 1659.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>MAtthew Caffin</hi> affirmed, <hi>That Chriſt and his Spirit was di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct one from the other;</hi> and at a Meeting at <hi>Henry Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſes</hi> at <hi>Ellſted</hi> in <hi>Surrey</hi> he declared and ſtood to affirm the ſame thing again before many people at that Meeting.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Here this deceiver goeth about to divide Chriſt, or to make people believe there is a dead Chriſt without a Spirit, for <hi>James</hi> ſaith, <hi>The body without the Spirit is dead,</hi> James 2. 26. and Chriſt ſaid, <hi>I am alive for evermore,</hi> Rev. 1. 18. and this deceiver hath falſly ſaid, we deny the Reſurrection; but now it is fallen upon his own head, for if Chriſts body were without a Spirit, then were it dead according to the Apoſtles Words, and if he were dead without a Spirit (according to the Baptiſts doctrine) then were he not riſen; ſo in effect
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:37340:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> he hath plainly denied the Reſurrection, but if thouſands ſhould deny him, yet he abideth faithful and lives forever; you may take notice there were ſuch that came among the <hi>Corinthians</hi> that were in contention, and <hi>Paul</hi> asked them whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Chriſt were divided? or was <hi>Paul</hi> crucified for them, as if one might be as poſſible as the other; but of a truth Chriſt is not divided, but he is both Lord and Chriſt, and the Lord is that Spirit which proceeded from the Father, and went again unto the Father, and he and the Father is one, and all that doth truly and rightly know theſe things, they muſt be converted into the light firſt, for great is the Myſtery of Godlineſs. And now if there be any ſo wilful as not to believe that <hi>Matthew Caffin</hi> is a deceiver, by all theſe fore-mentioned fruits of his, which are ſufficient proofes, (mark) then ſee how <hi>William Jeffery</hi> one of his chief brethren proves plainly that <hi>Matthew Caffin</hi> is led by the ſpirit of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt, and in a very deceitful ſecret way denies Chriſt come in the fleſh, but that ignorant envious man <hi>William Jeffery</hi> did intend that ſhould have been a proof againſt us, but it doth not at all concern us, for all people that hath heard and rightly underſtood our Doctrine of Chriſt and his Spirit, (which is in his body) they know we have declared Chriſt to be a quickening Spirit in his body, and alſo to be the head of the Church, which is his body, as the Scriptures ſaith, <note place="margin">Eph. 5. 30.</note> 
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 1. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. and the Saints were Members of his body, and of his fleſh and of his bones, and he was their head over them and in them all, <hi>Col.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 11. and ſo in his Name and Power do we preach him up to be the light within the body, and not apart from the body as <hi>Matthew Caffin</hi> hath affirmed him to be diſtinct the body from the Spirit; But how fit a proof hath <hi>William Jeffery</hi> brought againſt his brother and fellow-meſſenger <hi>Matthew Caffin</hi> in the 68 pag. of their own book with their names to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, in the 68 pag. <hi>William Jeffery</hi> his words chiefly is to prove them to be led by the ſpirit of errour, and the ſpirit of Antichriſt (mark) that preach up the Spirit of Chriſt apart from the body or fleſh of Chriſt, (and as it is before ſet down) <hi>Matthew Caffin</hi> did ſeveral times ſay and affirm, that Chriſt and his Spirit was diſtinct one from the other, and ſo the one of theſe proves the other to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:37340:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> be a deceiver, (mark) <hi>William Jeffery</hi> his words in the 68. page of that book (called the deceiving Quakers diſcovered) how plainly he proves his brother a deceiver, and alſo himſelf and the reſt of the Baptiſts, who do generally believe and ſay that the body or fleſh of Chriſt is above the skies, in ſome place they call Heaven, and his Spirit in them which hath been dipt in water, this is generally held forth by them, and ſo it is plain they do ſay the Spirit of Chriſt is in them a part from the body, which they ſay is above the skies in Heaven; but if it were as they ſay, then hath <hi>William Jeffery</hi> overthrown their whole faith (which is vain) &amp; proved them all deceived and deceivers as well as himſelf and <hi>Matthew Caffin;</hi> but with the light all moderate people may ſee theſe Baptiſts to be in the night (and not to have a Viſion) that could not ſee how <hi>William Jeffery</hi> went to overthrow their whole faith, before it came openly forth printed into the world; but now it is manifeſted their form is dead, and they in it appear na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedly, for all their high-ſwelling words, and to be all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived and deceivers; And for Zions ſake I cannot hold my peace, the love of God is ſo ſtrong in me unto ſimple-hearted poor Souls, but after the Fathers love is manifeſted unto them, and they reject it, then I may ſay as the Apoſtle ſaid, <hi>But if any be ignorant let him be ignorant,</hi> 1 Cor 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 38</p>
               <p>At a Meeting at <hi>Covole</hi> the 28th of the 6th month, 1659. the afore-mentioned <hi>Matthew Caffin</hi> (Baptiſt Teacher) affirmed, <hi>That Chriſt doth not come in us, that is, in their bodies;</hi> and he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſaid, <hi>He d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nied that to be Chriſt that was in people,</hi> and many words to that effect.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Theſe Baptiſts chief Principles are to deny the true Chriſt, at the Meetings where they come, and that exceeding boldly and impudently, as all ſober peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple may ſee that reads this with the leaſt meaſure of light; for that was the true Chriſt which all the true Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets bore witneſs of, and that <hi>Moſes</hi> writ of to come amongſt the people, and h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> did proceed from God, and dwelt amongſt <note place="margin">Joh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 14.</note> his Diſciples, and they beheld his glory, the glory, as of the onely begotten of the Father full of grace and truth, and he <note place="margin">John 14. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> told his Diſciples, he dwelleth with you and ſhall be in you, for ſaid he, <hi>I will not leave you comſortleſs, I will come to you,</hi>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:37340:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> John 14. 17, 18. and this was the true Chriſt the light of the world, and the eye of the body, who proceeded from the Father, and went unto the Father, and come again unto the Diſciples, which waited to know him that was to come and be in them, and he did come to them within, and the Antichriſts came unto them without, but greater was he that was in them, then he that was in the world, or they that were without them, and ſo by his power in them they withſtood the falſe prophets and Antichriſts, and then went they into the world, 1 <hi>John</hi> 4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. but Chriſt the Son whom the Father ſent to be the Saviour of the world, was then come again according to his former promiſe, and was in them and they in him, as it was ſaid in <hi>John</hi> 14. 20. and if you that read this, do not believe he did come again ſo ſoon to them, ſee what <hi>John</hi> ſaith, <hi>And we know the Son of God is come, and hath given us an underſtanding, that we may know him that is true, and we are in him that is true, even in his Son Jeſus Chriſt, this is the true God and Eternal life,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> John 5. 20. and ſo the Scriptures teſtifie of him to come and be in his Diſciples, and they in him; but the Baptiſts ſaith plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, he is not come in their bodies, and that is the ground why they are ſo inraged like the troubled Sea, becauſe they have reſiſted him that ſaid, <hi>Behold, I ſtand at the door and knock, if any man hear my voice and open the door, I will come into him,</hi> Rev. 3. 20. but the Baptiſts hath kept him out, and ſo are Reprobates concerning the Faith which he worketh in them that receive him at his coming; and the Apoſtles bid the <hi>Corinthians</hi> examine themſelves whether they were in the Faith, <hi>Prove your own ſelves, know you not your own ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lves how that Jeſus Chriſt is in you except you be Reprobates?</hi> 2 Cor. 13 5. and now all may ſee that they were Reprobates that d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d not know Jeſus Chriſt in them, and ſo are theſe Baptiſts now that do not know Jeſus Chriſt in them, and now is it ſeen and proved plainly that theſe Baptiſts are led by the ſpirit of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt in a reprobate ſtate, not confeſſing Chriſt to be come in the fleſh, but denying him in themſelves, which is the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry cauſe why they ſo wilfully reſiſt and gainſay him in others, where he is come up a ſwift witneſs againſt unrighteouſneſs; and ſo according to the Scriptures it is proved that the true Chriſt did come and dwell with his Diſciples in the form of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:37340:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> the fleſh, and did go away unto the Father, and came again unto his Diſciples according to his promiſe, and they knew he was come in them to dwell, but this was not after the fleſh, for they were to know him ſo no more, but as he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared, they were to ſee him as he is, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3. 2. and they did know him come in them a quickning Spirit, for by him were they quickned who had been dead in treſpaſſes and ſins, he that reads with the light may underſtand.</p>
               <p>And now I ſhall prove again he doth not onely deny Chriſt to be come in their bodies or fleſh, but he alſo denieth that to be the Chriſt that was in people; and now if you will at all regard the Scriptures of truth, with the light you ſhall ſee how plainly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhall prove out of the Scriptures that to be the true Chriſt the Son of the onely true God that was in people, that you may all ſee how the Baptiſts hath denied both the Father and the Son, and would go on deceiving and being deceived.</p>
               <p>Firſt ſee what Chriſt ſaith unto his Diſciples, <hi>At that day ye ſhall know that I am in my Father, &amp; you in me, and I in you,</hi> (Mark that) <hi>John.</hi> 4. 2. and ſo it is plain that Chriſt ſaid they ſhould know him in them which was the true Chriſt which lighteth every man that cometh into the world; and <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timothy</hi> ſaid, <hi>Howbeit for this cauſe I obtained mercy, that in me firſt Jeſus Chriſt might ſhew forth all long-ſuffering, for a pattern to them which ſhould hereafter believe on him to life everlaſting,</hi> 1 Tim. 1. 16. here the Apoſtle ſpeaks of the true Chriſt ſuffering in him, and firſt to ſhew it forth for a pattern (mark that) and <hi>Paul</hi> told the <hi>Galathians</hi> what a perſecutor he had been of thoſe that preached in the Name of Chriſt, while he was among the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing Jews; <hi>But when it pleaſed God who ſeparated me from my mothers womb, and called me by his gace to reveal his Son in me, that I might preach him among the Heathen,</hi> Gal. 1. 15, 16. and Chriſt was in them the Hope of Glory; and the Apoſtle ſaid, <hi>Little children of whom I travel in birth again until Chriſt be form<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> in you,</hi> Gal. 4. 12. and again the Apoſtle ſaid, <hi>but that with all boldneſs, as alwayes, ſo now alſo Chriſt ſhall be magnified in my body, whether it be by life or by death,</hi> Philip. 1. 20. and God was their Father, who was above all, and through all, and in <note place="margin">Eph. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> them all, and Chriſt was at the right hand of God in them
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:37340:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> all, and Chriſt lived in <hi>Paul,</hi> and he ſaid, <hi>The life that I now live in the fleſh, I live by the Faith of the Son of God,</hi> Galat. 2. 20. Many more Scriptures might be brought to prove that Chriſt was in people, whom the Father ſent to be the onely Saviour of the world; and that was the true Chriſt which was in them, and they were in him, as <hi>John</hi> ſaid, <hi>He is come that is true, and we are in him that is true, even in his Son Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> 1 John 5. 20. but theſe Bap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſts have denied him to be the Chriſt, <hi>And them will he deny before his Father which is in Heaven,</hi> Matth. 10 33. And ſo you may ſee how the Baptiſts preacheth Chriſt in words, but now when they are tried they deny him to be come in them, and alſo deny him in all others; and now it may be ſaid by ſome (that are ignorant of the things of God) that Chriſt did ſay unto his Diſciples, <hi>He would go away and come to them again, and be in them;</hi> and that the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſaid, <hi>He was come, and was in them;</hi> but yet they ſpeak of his coming to Judgement, and alſo of their waiting for him until he did come, and all this is true.</p>
               <p>I ſhall anſwer it in ſhort for the truths ſake; all that did wait and watch in a readineſs for his coming in them, they knew his appearance in them, and alſo the Reſurrection from the dead without, for he was manifeſt with them and revealed in them, and they preached him ſo to come in like manner unto others; and the Apoſtle bid them watch and wait for his coming, and the Apoſtles themſelves did meet with ſuch, and wait with them for his coming, and hoped to ſee him appear in them in due time unto whom he had been preached, and among whom they had laboured; and the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, <hi>My little children of whom I travel in birth again until Chriſt be formed in you,</hi> Gal. 4. 19. and ſo they looked for his coming into them, and for his appearance, even as we do now (in whom he is come to rule in our hearts) and the Apoſtles did look, and we do look for his co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming in the Clouds of Heaven, and all his holy Angels with him at the laſt to Judge the ſecrets of men, according to the everlaſting Goſpel; and this is the Word of truth to all that can recieve it.</p>
               <p>And now all you ſimple-hearted people which deſire to know the truth concerning water-baptiſm, and breaking of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:37340:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> outward bread, whether you have been dipt or would be dipt, if you were ſure God did require it of you, who have thought or do think water-baptiſm and breaking of outward bread had been commands of Chriſt to his Diſciples after his Reſurrection, and ſo to all believers after the Apoſtles deceaſe.</p>
               <p>And now in the fear of the Lord lend your ear and hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken diligently that your Souls may live, for in true love and pitty unto your poor Souls do I write unto you of theſe things, even as it hath been manifeſted unto me in the light which gives the true knowledge of the things of God unto they that are ſpiritual; And by the Revelation of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit I have perfect knowledge given unto me of thoſe thing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> which the natural man doth not know, becauſe they are ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually diſcerned, and revealed by the Spirit unto the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the Lord, to the praiſe and glory of our God, and to the comfort of their Souls which are redeemed out of death, to re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oyce in God the Saviour for ever.</p>
               <p>And when there doth ariſe in you a deſire to read and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand theſe things, then let your minds be turned unto the light of Chriſt in your Conſciences, which is ſo freely given unto you, for to make manifeſt that which may be known of God unto you, and in you, (mark) and when the mind is turned unto the light, then will the dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and ignorance be manifeſted to be within, which is the very cauſe why people doth not rightly underſtand the things of God when they ſpeak or read of them with their minds blinded, and the nobility of their underſtandings clouded with enmity againſt the light, and therefore doth not know thoſe things they read or ſpeak of (but naturally as bruit beaſts) yet will they be judging or ſaying this or that is their Judgement or Opinion; then, when they are contradicted, they wring or wreſt the Scriptures (to their own deſtruction) thinking thereby to uphold their Opinion, and ſo to get victory over one another, ſuch is the Phariſee practiſe, who love to have the praiſe of men (in theſe our dayes;) and therefore now you ſimple-hearted that would walk in the right way but do not know it, I do write unto you, that you may not be haſty, and ſo run raſhly into any opinion, but believe in the light in your own Conſcience, for he that <note place="margin">Iſa 28. 16.</note> believeth ſhall not make haſte, and then waiting in the light,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:37340:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> the power of God will ariſe in due time, and rent the vaile, and overturn the dark mountains, and ſo may you come to <note place="margin">Rom. 14. 5</note> be perſwaded in your minds; &amp; ſuch was the Apoſtles Doctrine when there was ſtriving or contending about dayes, even as there is among the chief Baptiſts now; and ſo now people may ſee the Baptiſts are gone into Opinions and Sects like the Prieſts, ſome for one thing and ſome for another, one Sect for free Will and another for Election (as they call them) and another Sect of them are among the ſhadows and figures obſerving the ſeventh dayes for their ſabbath, which God gave unto the Children of Iſrael for a ſign, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. and the Apoſtle ſaid unto the <hi>Coloſſians, Let no man therefore Judge you in meat or in drink, or in reſpect of an holy day, or of the new Moon, or of the Sabbath day, which are a ſhadow of things to come, but the body is of Chriſt,</hi> Coloſ. 2. 16, 17. Now they that do not go into the obſervation of the Sabbaths cannot be Judged in them by any man, (mark that) but the Apoſtle Judged ſome among the <hi>Galatians,</hi> ſaying, Ye obſerve dayes and moneths, I am afraid of you leaſt I have beſtowed my labour in vain, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. for his labour was to bring them out of the obſervation of dayes, and outward things, to Chriſt within, who is Lord of all days, yea he is and ſhall be known Lord of all, and therefore it is his right to Rule over all when he comes, and therefore be not offended when he would ariſe to Rule and Reign in you, for bleſſed are they that are not offended in him, who hath born the iniquity of us all, and he lighteth every man that cometh into the world, and that light is the Law of the Spirit, which is of him, and this Law is their Teacher that love it and are guided by it out of darkneſs unto Chriſt, which is the Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giver, that taketh away the ſin, and fulfills the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Law in man, and then man is at the end of the Law, with Chriſt, who brings in Grace and Peace and ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting righteouſneſs, within them that firſt become obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent <note place="margin">Gal. 3. 24.</note> unto the Law which is light within, which was our Schoolmaſter and the Apoſtles Schoolmaſter to bring them to Chriſt, who fulfilled thoſe viſible things in which he was in, and paſſed through, for in the time of Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion when eight dayes were accompliſhed for the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:37340:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> Circumciſing of the Child, they called his Name Jeſus, <hi>Luke</hi> 2. 21. and he was baptized of <hi>John</hi> in <hi>Jordan,</hi> for ſo he came unto <hi>John</hi> to fulfill that Miniſtration as well as Circumciſion, but <hi>John</hi> would not a had it ſo, yet Chriſt ſaid ſuffer it to be ſo now, for thus it becometh us to fulfill all righteouſnes; &amp; when he was baptized, then was not that fulfilled? (mark) ſtraight way he went out of the water, <hi>Mat.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 16. then began <hi>Johns</hi> Baptiſm to decreaſe, and Chriſts Baptiſm to increaſe which was more excellent, and ſo after Chriſt ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> been in the Synagogues and Temple made with hands and in water Baptiſm, he came <note place="margin">Mat. 23. 38.</note> out of them, and ſaid behold your houſe is left unto you deſolate, and he came ſtraight way out of the water, and left them there that would not leave that and follow him the fulfiller of all th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe things, into the Kingdom of reſt and peace <note place="margin">Joh. 3. 15. Pet. 4. 7.</note> for ever, (Mark) then they that abode in the Temple-worſhip cryed the Temple of the Lord, yet were in envy againſt Chriſt the Lord of all who left their Temple deſolate; and they that were baptized (after a little time) ran into contentions, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Chriſt was not among them in the water to keep them out of the contention, but then he had left both Temple and water, and they that did not leave thoſe things to follow him who is the Prince of peace, they were and are in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, in and about thoſe things wch were fulfilled, becauſe <note place="margin">1 Cor. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 11. 1 Cor. 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> Chriſt the Prince of peace was not with them, then to keep them out of the ſtrife contention and envy which they were in that did not follow Chriſt, who went ſtraightway out of the water, and out of the Temple and Synagogues and left them deſolate.</p>
               <p>But if any of you tender hearted ones ſhould be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, whether Chriſt did not command water Baptiſm after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>words unto his Diſciples when he ſent them forth to Preach and Teach.</p>
               <p>Now be low with your minds turned in to the light, wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the fear of the Lord, that you may be the ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>er to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand my anſwer, which ſhall be unto you according to the Scriptures, and I hope ſhall be plain to ſatisfie all rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable moderate people concerning water Baptiſm. For verily I ſay unto you I had never any command from the Lord to be baptized with outward water neither to Baptize any creature in outward water, but the Lord hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:37340:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> me to do that which is far greater and much more harder to the creature, but by the power of his Spirit in the light was I made able to do it, yet of my ſelf have I nothing to boaſt of, becauſe the work is the Lords, and the power by which it is done, and I his ſervant have ſaid unto ſome of thoſe Baptiſts Teachers, if they could prove water Baptiſm to be a command of Chriſt in this day, I ſhould own it, but they could never yet bring me any Scripture (that would ſerve for a plain proof) without wreſting, and alſo I have ſearched the Scriptures in which I find written how Chriſt ſent forth many Diſciples then, as now alſo, and I do not find any where in the Scriptures that he ſent them to Baptize in wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter after <hi>Johns</hi> Baptiſm decreaſed, there is in <hi>Matthew</hi> the 10. <hi>Mark 6. Luke</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. and 10. Chapters, how Chriſt ſent forth many Diſciples and commanded them what they ſhould do in his Name, but water Baptiſme is not mentioned there; but if any ſhould ſay he baptized then himſelf, for he was not crucified then,</p>
               <p>I anſwer and ſay, he did baptize, but his Baptiſm was not with water but with the Holy Ghoſt and with fire, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3. 11. and Chriſt ſaid verily, verily I ſay unto you, he that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth on me, the works that I do ſhall he do alſo, and greater works then theſe ſhall he do, becauſe I go unto my Father, <hi>John</hi> 14. 12. and ſo it doth appear <hi>Johns</hi> Miniſtry of Baptiſm was with water but Chriſts with the Spirit, for he both Circumciſed the heart and ears, and baptized with the Holy Ghoſt and with fire, which were ſpiritual things, and the Apoſtle ſaid therefore ſeeing we have this Miniſtry as we have received mercy we faint not, for they were believers, <note place="margin">2 C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 1.</note> and were to do the ſame works that Chriſt did, and ſo as he did ſo were they to do by the power of his Spirit in them; and all thoſe that believed, and came to be of the body (af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Chriſt Aſcended up on high) they were all baptized by one ſpirit into one body, the firſt of the <hi>Corinthians</hi> 12. 13. And the ſpirit was with them, and they with the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit did bring or baptize into the one body, by the power and ſword of the ſpirit which is the Word of God which they handled, ſo it is plain their works were ſpiritual, and their weapons were not carnal, but mighty through God, to the pulling down of ſtrong holds, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 4. and they Miniſtred
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:37340:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſpiritual things, 1 <hi>Cor</hi> 9. 11. and conſider rightly that place of Scripture the 28. of <hi>Matthew</hi> which the Baptiſts ſo often hath brought to prove water Baptiſm to be a command of Chriſt to his Diſciples, but that Scripture doth not at all ſpeak of water, and they are not onely wrong in putting water in the room of the Name of the Father, Son and Holy Ghoſt, but alſo in their not going forth into all the world to Preach the Goſpel to every creature, for ſo was that command, Mark 16. 15. <hi>And it is ſaid, go ye therefore and teach all Nations, Baptizing them in the Name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghoſt, Mat.</hi> 28. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>9. (Mark) there is nothing ſpoken at all of water, but there Chriſt commands them to teach and baptize in the Name of the Father, Son &amp; Holy Ghoſt, which Name ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth, for his Name is exalted above evety name, and is a ſtrong Tower, &amp; the righteous flee unto it and are ſafe, and ſo they <note place="margin">Pro 18. 10. Phil. 2. 9.</note> were to bring into or baptize in that which ſaved and kept them ſafe that believed through the Preaching of the Goſpel in the Name and power of God; but the Baptiſts ſay they that believe ſhould be baptized with water, as if there were no difference between the Name that ſaveth and a little wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which can do no more then the Hypocrites did which made clean the out-ſide, but were as filthy within as the Baptiſts are that are againſt the ſpirit and life it ſelf, for it is not the putting away the filth of the fleſh, but the anſwer of a good conſcience, by the Reſurrection of Jeſus Chriſt, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 21. and the Apoſtle ſaid there was one Lord, one Faith, <note place="margin">Eph. 4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> one Baptiſm, &amp; the ſpiritual Baptiſm is the onely Baptiſm wch by the power and the operation of the ſpirit that was in the Apoſtles they brought people into the one body which Chriſt was the head of, &amp; they baptized them in the Name, and there would Chriſt be in the midſt of them that met in his Name, to keep them in unity and peace, for he is the Prince of <note place="margin">Mat. 18. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Iſa. 9. 6.</note> peace, but thoſe Baptiſts that are in contention among themſelves, and in confuſion ſome for one thing and ſome for another, ſome obſerving one day for a Sabbath, and ſome obſerving another, they may perhaps have been bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized in water, but I am ſure they are not baptized by the one ſpirit into one body and Name of Chriſt, for then would Chriſt be in the midſt of them, to keep peace among them,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:37340:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> but there is bitterneſs, ſtrife and contention in the midſt of them, and Chriſt ſaid unto them that were baptized in his Name, and were to bapti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e in his Name, whatſoever they ask of the Father in his Name they ſhould receive it, and now let all the tender hearted Baptiſts be awakened to ſearch and examine themſelves whether they be in the faith; and have asked of God in the Name, or out of the Name of Chriſt; They ſur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly do know whether they have received that which they have asked for or not, and ſo may they come to know whether they have been baptized as Chriſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded in <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. or as the Baptiſts teachers hath imagined, and ſo they have wreſted that Scripture as they do others to their own deſtruction, and thereby hath deceived many others, making them believe water is there included, or that is a command for water, when water is not ſo much as menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned there, but the Name which ſaves all that are in it (mark) how plain the Scriptures proveth a great difference between water Baptiſme and the Baptiſm in the Name of the Father, Son and Holy Ghoſt, for there were ſome in the Apoſtles days that after they did believe were baptized into <hi>Johns</hi> Baptiſm, but they had not heard of the holy Ghoſt (mark) how they might have bin deceived with <hi>Johns</hi> Baptiſm had not they come to <hi>Paul</hi> who examined them about the matter, and found how they were led back into <hi>Johns</hi> Baptiſm, and then he taught them, and then they were baptized in the Name of the Lord Jeſus; for it is ſaid concerning <hi>Paul</hi> when he came to <hi>Epheſus,</hi> and finding certain Diſciples, he ſaid unto them, Have ye received the Holy Ghoſt ſince ye believed? and they ſaid unto him, we have not ſo much as heard whether there be any holy Ghoſt; and <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid unto them, unto what then were you baptized? and they ſaid unto <hi>Johns</hi> Baptiſm; then ſaid <hi>Paul, John</hi> verily baptized with the Baptiſm of repentance, ſaying unto the people, that they ſhould believe on him that ſhould come after him, that is on Chriſt Jeſus; when they heard this, they were baptized into the Name of the Lord Jeſus, <hi>Acts</hi> 19. from the firſt to the fifth verſe, and now ſee whether the chief Baptiſts have not need to be taught and baptized in the Name of the Lord Jeſus, for all their water Baptiſme, which was <hi>Johns</hi> Miniſtration? and now concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:37340:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> other Scriptures which hath been brought by the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts, as the 10. of the <hi>Acts,</hi> where <hi>Peter</hi> asked a queſtion in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed about water, but commanded them to be baptized in the Name of the Lord, and <hi>Philip</hi> Baptized the Eunuch in water but the name of the Father Son and Holy Ghoſt is not mentioned there, ſee <hi>Acts</hi> 8. 38. ſo it is plain there is a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction and great difference between water Baptiſm, and the Baptiſm of the ſpirit, or in the name that ſaveth, but ſome may ſay there was water ſpoken of, and practiſed by ſome, I ſay yes, they did in their freedom uſe water baptiſm, which was <hi>Johns</hi> Miniſtration, and <hi>Paul</hi> (who was not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde the very chiefeſt Apoſtle) for he ſaid he laboured more then them all, yet not I (ſaid he) but the Grace of God which was in him, and he did Baptize <hi>Criſpus</hi> and <hi>Gains</hi> and alſo the houſhold of <hi>Stephanus</hi> he baptized, but yet he thanks God he baptized no more of them, for he ſaid Chriſt ſent him not to baptize, but to Preach the Goſpel, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 17. and now it is plain if it could be proved that ſome of the Apoſtles were ſent to Baptize with water, that would be nothing to them now that ſpeak of baptizing with water, for what would that be to thoſe Baptiſts which dippeth in water now, ſeeing <hi>Paul,</hi> (who after them that Chriſt ſpake to in <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.) was made an able Miniſter of the Goſpel by the Revelation of Chriſt in him, and Chriſt ſent him among the <hi>Gentiles</hi> or heathen, not to Preach up water Baptiſm, and ſo to bring them into the water, (mark) but to Preach the Name of Chriſt among the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and to bring them into the name which ſaved them, and ſo all people that doth underſtand thoſe things may ſee all that ever the Baptiſts have done is but by imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation according to their imaginations, for if that which the Baptiſts bring for the proof of their command to Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize did not reach unto <hi>Paul,</hi> who was ſo eminent, ſurely it doth not reach unto theſe Baptiſts, but <hi>Paul</hi> did Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe, and baptize by permiſſion for a time as it doth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, that he might win the more out of thoſe old things (which was to paſſe away) unto Chriſt that maketh old things away, and then the new creature is witneſſed which availeth, for it is ſaid neither Circumciſion nor uncircumci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion avail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ech but a new creature, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6. 15. and ſo people may under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:37340:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> wherefore <hi>Paul</hi> (as well as others) did baptize, although they might not be ſent to Baptize nor Circumciſe, yet he did both, for he became all things to all that he might win ſome out of all, unto Chriſt the end of all things, that was to ſtand but their time, but when the Baptiſts were in ſtrife, one for <hi>Paul</hi> and others for <hi>Apollo</hi> and <hi>Cephas,</hi> but then they were carnal, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 3. and then <hi>Paul</hi> told thoſe Baptiſts plainly he was not ſent to Baptize, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 17. and <note place="margin">1 Cor. 1. 12.</note> ſome went to ſubvert thoſe believers (that were turned from among the <hi>Gent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>les</hi> nnto God) ſaying they muſt be Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed after the manner of <hi>Moſes,</hi> or elſe they could not be ſaved, but when the Apoſtles and Elders, and brethren, and the whole Church was met together at Jeruſalem (and when they had conf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rred about the matter, it ſeemed good unto the Holy Ghoſt and unto them to write letters and ſend them with choſen men, unto <hi>An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ioch,</hi> and this was the ſubſtance (which is there mentioned) of their letters, to let them know, they gave no ſuch command for Circumciſion, or ſuch things, (mark) and how they laid no greater burden upon them then theſe neceſſary things, ſaying that if ye abſtain from meats offered to Idols, and from blood, and from things ſtrangled and from fornication, from which if you keep your ſelves, ye ſhall do well, fare ye well, <hi>Acts</hi> 15. 25. and here you may ſee there was neither Circumciſion, nor obſerving the ſeventh day for a Sabbath, neither water Baptiſm or any ſuch things laid upon the Church that from among the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles</hi> were turned unto God, neither by the Holy Ghoſt, nor the general Aſſembly of Saints at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and therefore if any come among the people now, to cry up Circumciſion or water Baptiſm to be a command of Chriſt to us, becauſe there was Circumciſion with hands and water Baptiſm practiced before Chriſts Reſurrection, and after by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, yet the Scripture ſaith no greater burthen then theſe neceſſary things before mentioned in <hi>Acts</hi> 15. for we ſee now the Circumciſion is that of the heart, and the Baptiſm is with the ſpirit in the name which ſaves, and ſo now there is no need of thoſe old outward things becauſe the end of them is come within, which is Chriſt the better hope, and his B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ptiſm is with the ſpirit into the one body, and his Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:37340:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> is of the heart and ears, and ſo he ſitteth the true wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers to worſhip the Father in the ſpirit and in the truth, and ſuch are built upon the Rock (which the gates of Hell cannot prevail againſt) and therefore cannot be moved when the ſects of the Baptiſts or Prieſts, or they of the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion comes like the troubled Seas foaming out their own <note place="margin">Jude 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> ſhame againſt the Lamb and his followers who gets the victory over all through ſufferings, and bleſſed are all thoſe that wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>teth in the patience faithful unto the end.</p>
               <p>And now concerning outward bread and wine, which the Papiſts and the ſeveral Sects of the Prieſts, and likewiſe the Sects of the Baptiſts uſe concerning and pertaining to their worſhip, ſome calling of it the Sacrament, and ſome the Lords Supper, and every one uſeth thoſe good creatures according to their vain imaginations, and every Sect of them counts their own way right, to uſe bread and wine and <note place="margin">Pro. 16. 2</note> water, concerning their worſhip both Papiſts and Baptiſts, and all the other Sects of Prieſts which cry up viſible things to be Ordinances of Chriſt pertaining to their worſhip, and ſuch worſhips now is not the true worſhip of the true God the Father, for he is and ought to be worſhipped in the Spirit and in the truth; and all that are out of the Spirit in the viſible bread and wine &amp; water, they are the falſe worſhippers, both Papiſts and other Sects as well as they, for they are all ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the creatures more then to the Creator, who is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped in Spirit and in truth, and all the Statutes and Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances (after the fall into the tranſgreſſion) in reference to vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible things pertaining to the Worſhip of God in thoſe forms, was ordained in time for to ſtand their time as ſhadows, types &amp; figures of good things to come in due time, and the end of all thoſe things did come, and thoſe that did not know the end of all thoſe things come, to redeem the mind to God in due time (mark they Idolized them, and they were their Idols, ſet up out of their time by the Idolatrous worſhippers, <note place="margin">H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 1 Cor. 12. 31.</note> for in due time God ſent forth his Son, (a more excellent way) a new and living way, and they that received him in due time he changed them out of the old things which had their time to be ſet up and to ſtand until fulfilled, and then it was time for them to fall and have an end when Chriſt
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:37340:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> had been in them, and fulfilled them, and was come out of them again, and then will-worſhippers they ſought to hold them up out of their time, and thereby drew people from Chriſt into thoſe things; but Chriſt called out of thoſe things to take up the Croſs and follow him who fulfilled thoſe things, and he ſent (thoſe that followed him) forth to call others, which were without ready to periſh with thoſe things, and therefore to come into the Fathers houſe, for all things were ready there, &amp; they that would not forſake thoſe things and come into Chriſt where all things was ready, they ſhould <note place="margin">Luke 14.</note> not taſte of the Supper; and it is ſaid as they were eating, <hi>Jeſus took bread and bleſſed it, and brake it, and gave it unto his Diſciples, and ſaid, Take eat, this is my body, and he took the Cup and gave thanks, and gave it to them, ſaying, Drink ye all of it, for this is my blood of the New Teſtament which is ſhed for many, for the remiſſion of ſins,</hi> Matth. 26. 26. 1 Cor. 11. 24.</p>
               <p>And now both Papiſts and Baptiſts, and many other car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal-minded people imagineth that bread and the cup of Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to be outward bread and wine, and therefore they will be eating and drinking outward bread and wine, and when they have been asked to prove their practice to be a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of Chriſt by the Scripture, then they have run to thoſe Scriptures as if they would have proved ſomething for them, but we find thoſe Scriptures to be againſt them, for there it is ſaid in <hi>Matth. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>6. 1 Cor. 11. The Bread was his body which was broken for them, and the Cup was his blood which was ſhed for the remiſſion of ſins, but the natural man doth not know the things of God, becauſe they are ſpiritually diſcerned,</hi> 1 Cor. 2 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. and ſo they eat viſible creatures, and do not dicern the Lords Body; now the viſible bread and drink is for the ſatisfy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the hunger and thirſt of the viſible body, being recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in the fear of the Lord; but the bread of life, and the fruit of the heavenly Wine doth ſatisfie the hungry Soul, and the immortal Soul that hungereth and thirſteth after righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs cannot be ſatisfied without that Bread of Life and Blood which Chriſt gave unto his Diſciples, and with the light you may eaſily perceive that proved to be the ſpiritual meat, for Chriſt ſaid, <hi>I am the Bread which came down from Heaven,</hi> John 6. 41. but that troubled the profeſſing Jews,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:37340:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> even as our words of Truth doth trouble both Papiſts and the reſt of the Sects that uſe viſible bread, and ſet that in ſtead of the inviſible Bread of God which came down from Heaven and gives life unto the world, <hi>John 6. 33.</hi> and when we ſay the bread and drink which Chriſt gave unto his Diſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples was his body and blood according to the Scriptures, then they wonder, and ſome of them hath ſaid, how could he give them his body to eat and drink? and ſuch was the Jews car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal reaſon, when Chriſt ſaid, <hi>The bread that I will give, is my</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">John 6. 52</note> 
                  <hi>fleſh;</hi> then the Jews ſtrove among themſelves, ſaying, <hi>How can this man give us his fleſh to eat?</hi> then Jeſus ſaid unto them, <hi>Verily, verily I ſay unto you, except ye eat the fleſh of the Son of man, and drink his blood, you have no life in you,</hi> John 6, 51, 52, 53. but this was a hard ſaying unto the Jews, and alſo to the Diſciples that looked without at the fleſh and blood that was viſible, inſomuch that many were offended and went back, and walked no more with Jeſus, for he ſaid unto them, <hi>Doth this offend you?</hi> What and if you ſhall ſee the Son of man aſcend up where he was before, it is the Spirit that quickneth, the fleſh profiteth nothing, the words that I ſpeak unto you they are Spirit, and they are Life, <hi>verſ. 63.</hi> and ſo he did give his body and blood, and life unto his Diſciples, as he ſaid in <hi>Matth. 26.</hi> for he had life in himſelf to give <note place="margin">John 5. 26.</note> unto whom he would, and unto this agree thoſe Scriptures which ſpeaketh of heavenly and ſpiritual gifts that were given unto the Saints which were to feed the flock of God with that which they had received, and they did feed ſome with the milk of the Word that were as new born babes, and <note place="margin">1 Cor 3 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Heb <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> ſome with ſtrong meat as they were able to bear it; and ſo they broke bread, or devided the Word aright as good ſtew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards of the manifold grace of God, 1 Pet. 4. 10 and ſo that which they received of the Lord they miniſtred unto others <note place="margin">1 Tim. 2. 15.</note> according to their gift or ability, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid (after he had asked the <hi>Corinthians</hi> whether they had not houſes to eat and to drink in) <hi>For I have received of the Lord that which alſo I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered unto you,</hi> 1 Cor. 11. 23. and they had received the word of reconciliation, and the life and truth it ſelf, and that they declared and delivered a right according to every ones ability, and ſo they break bread from houſe to houſe as <note place="margin">Acts 2. 46.</note>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:37340:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> the Scripture ſaith, <hi>And they kept the Feaſt, but not with the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>aven of malice and wickedneſs, but with the unleavened bread of ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ncerity and truth,</hi> 1 Cor.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. and this was their manner of breaking of bread, or miniſtring ſpiritual things, who did not handle the Word of God deceitfully, but devided that a right which they had ſeen, taſted and handled, which was <note place="margin">2 C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r. 4. 2. Heb. 6 5, 1 John 1. 1.</note> good unto them, whoſe affections were ſet upon things above thoſe natural things which the natural man looketh at.</p>
               <p>Now you may ſee there is not a word in Scripture that ever Chriſt or the Apoſtles did Command breaking of outward vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible bread, but Chriſt (whoſe Words were Spirit &amp; Life) ſaid, <hi>I am the bread that came down from Heaven, that a man may eat of and not dye;</hi> again he ſaid, <hi>Except ye eat the fleſh of the Son of man and drink his blood, ye have no life in you,</hi> John 4. and the true worſhippers worſhip the Father in Spirit and in truth, and he that eateth of Chriſts body (the bread of Life) ſhall live by him, ſaid Chriſt, <hi>John 6. 57.</hi> and he ſaid the bread that he brake and gave to his Diſciples was his body, and the cup was his blood which he gave them, then (mark) what he ſaid, <hi>But I ſay unto you, I will not drink henceforth of this fruit of the vine until that day when I drink it new with you in my Fathers Kingdom,</hi> John. 5. 1. and he that will drink of the fruit of this vine with Chriſt, muſt firſt come into the Kingdom of God, for there is the Throne and Table of the Lord known; and when one of them that ſate at meat with him heard theſe things, he ſaid unto him, <hi>Bleſſed is he that ſhall eat bread in the Kingdom of God,</hi> Luke 14. 15. Here it ſpeaks of eating and drinking in the Kingdom of God, but the natural Jews and Baptiſts doth not know how thoſe things ſhould be, becauſe they are ſpiritually diſcerned, and ſo they deceive themſelves and others, that ſet up and cry up viſible things in the room of that which is inviſible, and ſuch beguile people in a vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary humility, intruding into thoſe things which they have not ſeen, vainly puft up by their fleſhly, earthly and ſenſual knowledge, and not holding the head, ſuch the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle <hi>Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l</hi> ſpeaks of to the <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſians,</hi> that they might be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of them, ſaying, <hi>Wherefore if ye be dead with Chriſt from the rudiments of the world, why as though living in the world are ye ſubject to Ordinances? touch not, taſte not, handle not, which</hi>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:37340:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
                  <hi>all are to periſh with the uſing after the commandments and doctrines of men, which things have indeed a ſhew of wiſdom, in will-worſhip and humility, and neglect of the body,</hi> Col 2. And ſo in love and pitty unto poor Souls have I freely declared and rightly proved that which firſt I received of the Lord in the Light which gives the right underſtanding, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that can receive them, let him do it freely in the Light.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
